Finding Aid for the Collection of Material about Japanese American Incarceration LSC.0131
UCLA Library Special Collections
Collection of Material about Japanese American incarceration
1929-1956
1942-1946
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.0131
4.6 Linear Feet (4 boxes and 1 oversize folder)
The collection consists of publications and press releases by the United States War Relocation Authority (WRA), in addition to yearbooks and pamphlets created by Japanese American incarcerees and advocacy groups, with an emphasis on the Manzanar and Minidoka incarceration camps.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIO MATERIALS: Materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ralph P. Merritt, 1946. Additional items are the gift of Bradford Smith, 1952.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942327683606533
Scope and Content
The collection consists primarily of materials from the United States War Relocation Authority related to Japanese Americans and forced removal. Included are various War Authority publications and pamphlets; The Minidoka irrigator, a weekly newspaper published at the Minidoka Relocation Center (Hunt, Idaho); camp newsletters from Puyallup Assembly Center (unofficially called Camp Harmony); and miscellaneous publications related to the Manzanar inconcentration camp in Owens Valley, CA. In addition are yearbooks and pamphlets created by Japanese American incarcerees and advocacy groups, such as the Japanese American Citizens League (JACL), with an emphasis on the Manzanar and Minidoka incarceration camps; and speeches, clippings of published articles, and Master's theses. The collection also includes a recording of The Exile's Return, a production of CBS-KNX News (1956) and several reproduced sketches by artist Mine Okubo.
Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
War Relocation Authority (WRA), 1942-1946
Incarceration camps, 1942-1945
Miscellaneous, 1929-1956.
Related Materials
Manzanar War Relocation Center records (Collection 122). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Japanese American Research Project collection of material about Japanese in the United States (Collection 2010). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Japanese Americans -- Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945; Concentration camps -- United States; Concentration camp inmates' writings; United States--War Relocation Authority.
- Series 1: War Relocation Authority (WRA), 1942-1945
  Scope and Contents
  Publications and speeches sponsored by the War Relocation Authority (WRA). Includes annual and semi-annual reports for the years 1942 through 1946, assorted pamphlets advocating Japanese American incarceration, resettlement, and enlistment in the armed forces, and transcripts of speeches by Dillon S. Myer, Director of the WRA.
  Existence and Location of Copies
  This series has been digitized. Digital reproductions of materials in this series are available online at https://digital.library.ucla.edu/catalog/ark:/21198/z1wm32vb.
  - Quarterly report, 1942 March 18-June 30. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Report includes chronology detailing incarceration process from 1941 December 7 to 1942 June 29 and gives brief descriptions of incarceration camp sites.
  - Quarterly report, 1942 July 1-September 30. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Report covers employment statistics within incarceration camps, leave regulations, college student forced removal, and general aspects of life in incarceration camps, such as education, mess operations, religious activities, and the fears and anxieties of incarcerees.
  - Quarterly report, 1942 October 1-December 31. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Report covers general aspects of life in incarceration camps, including forced removal progress, employment of incarcerees, and repatriation. Included is a description of a strike at the Potson camp and a riot at Manzanar.
  - Semi-annual report, 1943 January 1-June 30. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Report covers general aspects of life in incarceration camps, including mess hall operations, recreation, and education. Also details Senate Sub-committee investigation, Spanish Consular visit, isolation procedures, and segregation procedures for pro-Japanese and pro-American incarcerees.
  - Semi-annual report, 1943 July 1-December 31. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Report covers general aspects of life in incarceration camps, including segregation process and problems. Details Tule Lake Incident and November 1 demonstration at Tule Lake Hospital. Fold-out map of Tule Lake included.
  - Semi-annual report, 1944 January 1-June 30. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Documents the WRA's transfer from independent war agency to Department of the Interior. Includes general description of life in incarceration camps, including reaction of incarcerees and enlistment. Includes report of the House Sub-Committee on the Tule Lake Incident, the closing of the Jerome Relocation Center, and tables and charts showing average incarceration camp populations.
  - Semi-annual report, 1945 January 1-June 30. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Report discussed resettlement procedures, housing problems, incarceree attitudes, the children's village at Manzanar, and labor attitudes of the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) and the American Federation of Labor (AFL). Details the West Coast opposition toward Japanese American resettlement, including boycotts, terrorist incidents, and legal issues regarding ownership of property.
  - Semi-annual report, 1945 July 1-December 31. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Report summarizes resettlement, liquidation, and departure process from various incarceration camps. Resettlement issues of Tule Lake incarcerees are discussed, including renunciants and the declining influence of the Hoshidan (pro-Japanese societies).
  - Final semi-annual report, 1946 January 1-June 30. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Report documents the end of the WRA, as of June 30, 1946, including the forced removal of Tule Lake residents; renunciant hearings; closing of Tule Lake; and a general summary of incarceration processes.
  - Address. Ben Kuroki, 1944 February 4. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Address by Sergeant Ben Kuroki, U.S. Army Air Force, before the Commonwealth Club, San Francisco, CA (sponsored by the WRA). Details Kuroki's experience with racial prejudice while in the army, and calls for the humane treatment of Japanese Americans in the future. Kuroki was previously awarded with two Distinguished Flying Cross Medals.
  - Address. Dillon S. Myer. "One Thousandth of A Nation", 1944 March 23. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Address by the Director of the WRA, before a joint meeting of civic organizations in Salt Lake City, UT. Includes descriptions of life in the incarceration camps, and argues for the resettlement of Japanese Americans.
  - Address. Dillon S. Myer. "Problems of Evacuee Resettlement in California", 1945 June 19. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Address by the Director of the WRA in Eagle Rock, CA. Provides brief overview of forced removal process after 1943 and argues for resettlement of Japanese Americans.
  - Address. Dillon S. Myer. "Relocation Problems and Policies", 1944 March 14. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Address by the Director of the WRA, before the Tuesday Evening Club in Pasadena, CA. Details the operations of the incarceration centers in response to Hearst newspapers' claims that incarcerees were coddled; Meyer also contends that Japanese Americans must be protected and allowed to resettle.
  - Address. Dillon S. Myer. "The Facts About the War Relocation Authority", 1944 January 21. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Address by the Director of the WRA, before a luncheon meeting of the Los Angeles Town Hall, Los Angeles, CA.
  - Community Government in War Relocation Centers, 1946. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Report on the development of internal governments run by incarcerees. Subjects include the problems and confusion surrounding the Poston Strike and Manzanar Riot, community organization, and the future of Japanese American communities.
  - The Evacuated People: A Quantitative Description, 1946. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Report on the experiences of incarcerees at incarceration camps, moving, segregation, settling into camps, and resettlement.
  - Impounded People: Japanese Americans in the Relocation Centers, 1946. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Report on constitutional issues involved in the forced removal process, the WRA's legal framework, and the organization of the Office of the Solicitor.
  - Legal and Constitutional Phases of the WRA Program, 1945. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Pamphlet designed to ease agitation and anti-Japanese American sentiment. Questions addressed include: Japanese religion and ties to emperor, Japanese Language Schools, Nisei (a person born in the US or Canada whose parents were immigrants from Japan) in the Army, honesty of the Japanese as a race, assimilability of the Japanese, agricultural Competition, and coddling by the WRA.
  - "Message from the National Director to the Residents of Relocation Centers", 1945 July 12. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Open letter instructing incarcerees about resettlement, including timely departure from incarceration camps and camp closing dates.
  - Myths and Facts About the Japanese Americans: Answering Common Misconceptions Regarding Americans of Japanese Ancestry, 1945. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Reprinted newspaper articles on the bravery and sacrifices of Japanese American soldiers in World War II. Newspapers include Los Angeles Times, Tacoma News-Times, Chicago Tribune, and Omaha World Herald.
  - Nisei in the War Against Japan, 1944. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Illustrated pamphlet on Japanese Americans in the 442nd Regimental Combat Team and 100th Battalion. Includes an article about Ben Kuroki, the only American of Japanese descent in the United States Army Air Forces to serve in combat operations in the Pacific theater of World War II.
  - Nisei in Uniform, 1945. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Pamphlet on the segregation of Tule Lake incarcerees, including living conditions, improvement in public attitudes, and the records of Japanese American soldiers.
  - Press releases, 1944. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    WRA press releases on subjects related to incarcerees. Two items commemorate the military service of Japanese Americans, including the 110th Battalion and the 442nd Regimental Combat Team.
  - Relocating Japanese Americans, 1946. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Statistics on incarcerees, including marriage and divorce rates, numbers of renunciants, population at Tule Lake, and age composition of incarceration camp populations. Gift of Bradford Smith.
  - The Relocation Program, 1946. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Historic overview of the WRA and events leading to its creation. Includes early incarceration policies, forced removal processes, and resettlement. Gift of Bradford Smith.
  - The War Relocation Work Corps: A Circular of Information for Enlistees and Their Families, 1942. (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Pamphlet for Japanese Americans about incarceration camps, including family life, health, education, household effects, and the War Relocation Work Corps.
  - Wartime Exile: The Exclusion of the Japanese Americans From the West Coast, 1946. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Report on the justification for incarceration of Japanese and Japanese Americans, including a history of Japanese travels to North America beginning 1610, and general descriptions of Japanese and Japanese American populations in San Francisco, Los Angeles, Sacramento, Portland, and Seattle. Gift of Bradford Smith.
  - The Wartime Handling of Evacuee Property, 1946. (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Report on property issues created by incarceration, including the raid on Nichiren Temple, Los Angeles. Gift of Bradford Smith.
  - War Time Authority Community Government Handbook: A Summation of the Functions, Organization, and Relocationships of the Council of Administration, 1943. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Summary of the organization, techniques, function, and objectives of incarceration camp Community Councils in 1942-1943.
  - "What We're Fighting For": Statements by United States Servicemen about Americans of Japanese Descent, 1944. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Pamphlet attesting to the loyalty of Nisei soldiers.
- Series 2: Incarceration camps, 1942-1945
  Small publications, including yearbooks and newsletters, written and produced by Japanese American incarcerees from the Manzanar and Minidoka incarceration camps, and the Camp Harmony temporary detention center in Puyallup, Washington.
  - A Barrack Becomes A Home: A Cooperative Project in Homemaking by the Students of the Home Economics and Woodshop Departments of the Manzanar Secondary School, 1945 January 5. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Pamphlet prepared by Beatrice White, Home Economics Supervisor, Manzanar Secondary Schools, documenting class projects. Includes photographs of a typical Manzanar barrack interior and of altered barracks.
  - Camp Harmony Newsletter, v. I no. 4-8 (complete run), 1942 May-June. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Camp Harmony Assembly Center newsletter, Puyallup, Washington. Includes articles on daily life in the incarceration camp, such as conditions, sports, school, the temporary detention center, and employment.
  - Camp Harmony Newsletter, v. I no. 9-11 (complete run), 1942 July-August. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Education Section Summary, 1945 May 31. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Report on the closing of Manzanar's education system, prepared for Ralph P. Merritt for the WRA. Includes brief overview of pre-school, elementary, secondary school, adult education programs, and library systems. Final page includes signatures of Manzanar education staff. Cover artwork by Takamura, 1942.
  - Lil Dan'l: One Year In A Relocation Center, 1943. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Limited edition pictorial review documenting the first year of life in the Rohwer incarceration camp. Designed and illustrated by George Akimoto.
  - Manzanar High School Yearbook, "Cardinal and Gold", 1943. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Soft cover yearbook for the Manzanar incarceration camp graduating class of summer 1943.
  - Manzanar High School Yearbook, "Our World: Manzanar, California", 1943-1944. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Hardcover yearbook for the Manzanar incarceration camp graduating class of 1944. Illustrated.
  - Manzanar High School Yearbook, "Valediction", 1945. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Soft cover yearbook for the Manzanar incarceration camp graduating class of 1945. Illustrated.
  - Manzanar Libraries and Visual Aid Program, 1945 January 2. (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Report prepared by Ruth Budd, Director of School and Community Libraries. Report covers library history, staff training, fiction library, high school and elementary division. Includes black and white photographs of staff and facilities.
  - Minidoka Irrigator, v. I no. 15-20 (complete run), 1942 November. (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Minidoka incarceration camp newsletter. Includes articles on daily life in the camp, such as conditions, sports, school, and employment. Also includes a Japanese Language section on the back page with a brief English guide.
  - Minidoka Irrigator, v. I no. 4-14 (incomplete run), 1942 September-October. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Senior Edition: The Spot, v. III no. 7, 1944 April 6. (Box 4, Folder 12)
    Student newsletter from Manzanar. Includes senior class wills of last graduating class from Manzanar High.
  - Toy Loan Library, ca. 1944. (Box 4, Folder 13)
    Pamphlet on the Manzanar Toy Loan Project, began in 1944. Topics include founding, organization, objectives, floor plan, and mimeographed forms used by the Center. Booklet also includes six black and white photographs of children at the Toy Loan Center.
  - Trek, v. 1 no. 1., 1942 January 12. (Box 4, Folder 14)
    Special publication of Reports Division, Central Utah Relocation Project (Topaz), compiled by camp incarcerees. Consists of short stories, essays, and a biographical sketch of Mine Okubo. Includes artwork by Mine Okubo.
- Series 3: Miscellaneous, 1929-1956
  This series contains assorted printed materials including articles, publications, and clippings; a World War II recruiting poster; speeches; and Master's theses. Also included is a recording of a radio broadcast. Creators include the Japanese American Citizens League (JACL), the American Council on Public Affairs, the Fellowship of Reconciliation, and various individuals.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIO MATERIALS: Materials will require assessment and may need further processing for safe access. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
  - Audio recording: "Minority Report III: The Exile's Return", 1956 July 1. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Two 10-inch vinyl records encompassing Parts 1-4 of a special report on the Japanese American community in Los Angeles. Originally broadcast over KMX on July 1, 1956 (production of CBS-KNX News in cooperation with The Fund For The Republic).
  - Carter, Genevieve. "Child Care and Youth Problems In A Relocation Center", 1944. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Reprint from the Journal of Consulting Psychology (v. III no. 4), p. 219-225. Topics include the influence of the non-citizen parents on their citizen children, youth and delinquency, and the problems of younger children.
  - Casey, Gene. "G.I. Japyank", 1944 August 5. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Reprinted by the WRA, with permission from Collier's. Includes interview with Private Mac Yazawa.
  - Clark, Blake and Russell, Oland. "Hail Our Japanese-American GIs!", 1945 July. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Condensed reprint from the American Mercury. Describes heroic acts by members of the 100th Infantry Battalion and the 442nd Infantry Regiment.
  - The Displaced Japanese-Americans, 1944. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Pamphlet published by the American Council on Public Affairs; text originally appeared in Fortune, April 1944, under the title "Issei, Nisei, and Kibei." Defends the position of WRA against the Hearst newspapers, and describes life of the incarcerees. Calls for protection of civil liberties. Includes artwork by Mine Okubo.
  - Excerpts and clippings, 1944. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Excerpts from American newspapers regarding Japanese Americans. Newspapers include: The Courier (Camden, NJ); Arizona Republic (Phoenix, AZ); The Register (Des Moines, Iowa); The Tribune (Cheyenne, WY); The Record (Philadelphia, PA); Salt Lake Tribune (Salt Lake City, UT); Herald and American (Chicago, IL). Topics include employment, Nisei volunteers in the armed forces, and Japanese American resentment of Japanese brutality to prisoners of war.
  - Foote, Caleb. Outcasts! The Story of America's Treatment of Her Japanese-American Minority, 1944. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Illustrated pamphlet. Text questions the constitutionality of incarceration, citing racial prejudice and political pressure as the dominant forces behind incarceration; describes life in the camps. loyalty, and assimilation issues.
  - "Hawaii Soldiers Died Fighting As Loyal Americans, Col. Fielder Says", 1944 March 13. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Copy of an address delivered by Col. Kendall Fielder on the presentation of Purple Hearts to the families of 60 Japanese American soldiers killed in action in Italy. Photographic illustrations, with an article by Elmont Waite describing the ceremony.
  - "Klu-Kluxism on the West Coast", 1945 July 14. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Illustrated article from Collier's, denouncing the Japanese American Exclusion League.
  - Message from the President of the United States: "Segregation of Loyal and Disloyal Japanese in Relocation Centers", 1943 September 14. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Message before the 78th Congress, 1st session, transmitting a report on Senate resolution no. 166 relating to segregation of loyal and disloyal Japanese in incarceration camps.
  - Morimitsu, George. "These Are Our Parents", 1943 October. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Reprint from the Oct. 1943 issue of Asia and the Americas. Details the cultural and generational gap between Isei and Nisei, beliefs and values of Isei.
  - Nishimura, M.S., et al. "The Propagation of Guayule from Cuttings", 1944 July. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Reprint from the American Journal of Botany (v. 31 no. 7), p. 412-418.
  - O'Brien, Robert. "Reaction of the College Nisei to Japan and Japanese Foreign Policy", 1945 January. (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Reprint from the Pacific Northwest Quarterly (v. 36 no. 1). Article on the experience of Nisei college students before the bombing of Pearl Harbor, and their reaction to recruitment efforts of Japanese government.
  - O'Brien, Robert. "Selective Dispersion As a Factor in the Solution of the Nisei Problem", 1944 December. (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Reprint from Social Forces (v. 22 no. 2). Article examines dispersion of second generation Japanese Americans through college education as solution to assimilation process.
  - Rice, Richard B. The Manzanar Relocation Center, 1947 August. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Thesis. Attempts to trace the forces which created a democratic way of life in Manzanar. Topics covered include forced removal, WRA, Relocation Program, early history of Manzanar, employment problems at camp, problems with community government, and special projects.
  - Spier, Leslie. "Growth of Japanese Children Born in America and Japan", 1929 July. (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Reprint from the University of Washington Press, University of Washington Publications in Anthropology (v. 3 no. 1), p. 1-30. Topics include observations of body characteristics of Japanese children born in the United States and Japan such as length of head, width of face, and average age of loss of teeth.
  - Sproul, Robert Gordon. Address: "The test of a free country...", 1944 June 29. (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Copies of a speech by Dr. Robert Gordon Sproul, President of the University of California, at the California Club, Los Angeles, Calif. for the Pacific Coast Committee on American Principles and Fair Play.
  - Stearns, Marjorie. The History of the Japanese People in Oregon, 1937 July. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    University of Oregon Thesis Series. Topics include settlement of the Japanese in Oregon, relations between the Japanese and white residents, and anti-Japanese legislation.
  - Tatsumi, Henry S. Language Maps: Comparative Syntactic Charts for Japanese and English, ca. 1949. (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Visual aid illustrating the patterns of Japanese and English language structure.
  - They Work for Victory: The Story of Japanese Americans and the War Effort, 1945. (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Illustrated promotional pamphlet published by the Japanese Americans Citizens League (JACL). Advocates the efforts of Nisei, specifically service in armed forces and Nisei women working in manufacturing plants. Includes photographs of sculptor Isamu Noguchi and Ballerina Sono Osato.
  - Town Meeting, v. 11 no. 21. Transcript: "Who Should Control the Atomic Bomb?", 1945 September 20. (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Transcript of radio broadcast sponsored by the American Broadcasting Company. Moderated by George V. Denny, Jr. Speakers: Raymond Swing, Hanson Baldwin, Owen Brewster, and Edward R. Murrow.
  - United States. Dept. of the Interior. Division of Budget and Administrative Management. People in Motion: The Postwar Adjustment of the Evacuated Japanese Americans, 1947. (Box 3, Folder 22)